Guide to the Board of Trustees records, 1821-2003 RG0001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- George Washington University's charter, 1821-1988; RG0001 Series 4; 1 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 1)
  - An Act supplemental to the Act of February ninth, eighteen hundred and twenty-one, incorporating the Columbian College in the District of Columbia, and the Acts amendatory thereof, 03/18/1898 (Box 1, Folder 10.1)
  - University Charter, Amendments, & Supplementary Acts (Charter, Ordinances & By-laws of the Columbian University), 05/31/1899 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charter, Ordinances, and By-laws of the Columbian University, 05/31/1899 (Box 1, Folder 11.1)
  - University Charter, Amendments, & Supplementary Acts (Secularization & Change of Name), 01/23/1904 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum: Legislative History of the Act Which Authorized the Board of Trustees to Change the Name of the University, 02/26/1960 (Box 1, Folder 12.1)
  - Columbian University: Charter and By-laws, 1821 -1904 (Box 1, Folder 12.2)
  - Public Act No. 7: An Act Supplemental to the Act of February ninth, eighteen hundred and twenty-one, incorporating the Columbian College in the District of Columbia, and the Acts amendatory thereof, 01/23/1904 (Box 1, Folder 12.3)
  - University Charter, Amendments, & Supplementary Acts (Update), 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Public Act No. 200: An Act Supplemental to the Act of February ninth, eighteen hundred and twenty-one, incorporating the Columbian College in the District of Columbia, and the Acts amendatory thereof, 03/03/1905 (Box 1, Folder 13.1)
  - Part One: The Charter and Acts Supplementary Thereto, circa 1905 (Box 1, Folder 13.2)
  - University Charter, Amendments, Supplementary Acts (Update), 02/1910 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Charter of The George Washington University-February, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 14.1)
  - University Charter, Amendments & Supplementary Acts (Act Giving the University Certain Powers), 10/22/1970 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The George Washington University Charter Restatement Act, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1.1)
  - The Charter and Acts Supplementary Thereto of the George Washington University, undated (Box 2, Folder 1.2)
  - The Governance of The George Washington University: Report of the Commission on Governance of the University, 05/1971 (Box 2, Folder 1.3)
  - University Charter, Amendments, & Supplementary Acts. (Charter Restatement Act: Hearings & Markups Before the Subcommittee on Judiciary & the Comm. on the District of Columbia: 95th Congr., 1st Session, Serial No. 95-8, 05/03/1977 --09/19/1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - The Charter of The George Washington University, 01/04/1977 (Box 2, Folder 2.1)
  - University Charter, Amendments, & Supplementary Acts (Charter Restatement Act), 10/18/1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ordinance Providing for the Organization and Conduct of the Department of Public Health, with Courses of Study, etc., 02/20/1904 (Box 3, Folder 1.1)
  - Private Law 95-8: An Act to amend the Act of February 9, 1821, to restate the charter fo the George Washington University, 10/18/1977 (Box 3, Folder 1.2)
  - By-laws of The George Washington University, 05/18/1978 (Box 3, Folder 1.3)
  - The George Washington University Charter Restatement Act, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 1.4)
  - "House OKs Change in GW Charter"-Hatchet, v.74 no.9, 10/03/1977 (Box 3, Folder 1.5)
  - Folder 4, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Part One: The Charter and Acts Supplementary Thereto, undated (Box 4, Folder 1.1)
  - Binder containing Charter, as well as historical and statistical information of George Washington University. Also includes copy of George Washington's will, 1930 -1946 (Box 4, Folder 1.2)
  - The Charter and Acts Supplementary Thereto, with corrections written in ink, along with bound copy, undated (Box 4, Folder 1.3)
- Committees, 1911-1960; RG0001 Series 5; 4 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  This series is a collection of the meeting minutes and correspondence of the following Board of Trustees' committees: educational policy, alumni relations, building lands, endowment funds, executive committee, finance, university hospital, personnel, and libraries. They range in date from 1911 to 1960.
  - Committee on Educational Policy--Miscellaneous correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/11/1961 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Text on folder "The committee voted to recommend to the Board the proposals concerning the merger of the Junior College with Columbian College, to be effective Sept. 1, 1961,. The new name for the College will be the Columbian College of Arts and Sciences. The meeting adjourned."
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/03/1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Text on folder "Approval of recommendation that the Juris Doctor Degree be discontinued as a first degree of law effecive with respect to students entering the Law School in the 1961-62 academic year. Approval of "A Future Educational Policy for the School of Medicine" Approval of change in name and organization of the School of Government. The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Text on folder "The Committee on Educational Policy by correspondence, approved the recommendation that the regulations regarding the 21 tuition scholarships for full-time students in the Law School be amended, so that any scholarships that are open due: 1) to lack of qualified applicants 2) to resignations prior to entry into Law School 3) to resignations during residence in Law School, or 4) to failure to meet scholarship requirements shall be available to students with "B" averages who have completed one or two years of work."
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/03/1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "Tentative approval of the proposed revision of the "Ordinances and Code" Governing the Academic Personnel" pending its presentation to and approval by the Academic Council. To be presented to the Board on May 9, 1957. Discussion of the status of retired administrative officers."
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/29/1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Text on folder "Minutes of the Joint Meeting of the Executive Committee and the Committee on Educational Policy June 29, 1954 at 12:30 o'clock. For signed minutes, see Executive Committee folder."
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/06/1952 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Text on folder "THE MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE COMMITTEE ON EDUCATIONAL POLICY OF THE BOARD OF TRUSTEES, October 6, 1952. Admissions policies discussed. Reference to graduate students, veterans of the Korean war, nurses in The GWU Hospital and students recommended by government departments."
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/01/1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Text on folder "Re: Dean of School of Engineering Gallinger Hospital"
  - Committee on Educational Policy--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/02/1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Text on folder "Re: School of Applied Arts Scholarships to Evening High Schools"
  - Committee on Alumni Relations--meeting minutes, 12/1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Alumni Relations--meeting minutes, 06/22/1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Text on folder "MINUTES OF THE ALUMNI RELATIONS COMMITTEE June 22, 1960. The proposed new Articles of Association and By-Laws of the General Alumni Association were considered. The following recommendations were adopted by the Committee: 1) the Committee concurs in principle with the Articles and By-Laws and will recommend approval to the Board subject to some qualifications. The meeting adjourned."
  - Committee on Alumni Relations--meeting minutes, 03/13/1930 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Text on folder "Re: Equipment of Alumni Offices Recognition of Alumni in 1932 February Convocation"
  - Committee on Building Lands, Correspondence, 1950 -1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/28/1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Text on folder "JOINT MEETING OF THE COMMITTEES ON FINANCE AND BUILDINGS AND LANDS November 28, 1960 (Signed minutes filed in Finance Committee folder.)"
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/29/1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Text on folder "Negotiations under way for purchase of Lot 17, Sq. 119 (1912 Pa. Ave.). The Committee authorized an offer of $42,000 for this property. (If necessary $45,000) Committee advised of offers to sell 1916 G Street (Lot E, Sq. 120) to the University for $25,000. The Committee took no action regarding this property. The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/18/1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Text on folder "Report of real estate purchases made since Sept. 1, 1959 under authority granted by Board on Oct 8, 1959. Authority granted to the Committee by the Board Oct 8, 1959, was amended to permit purchases within a total expenditure of $600,000 (instead of $400,000). It was further provided that the limitation of $600,000 be increased by purchase price of Liberty Baptist Church property if the property is authorized by the Board. Liberty Baptist Church property was considered. Approval of recommendation to the Board that property be purchased at a price of $180,000. Approval of purchase of property at 1916 H St. N.W. for $20,000 and properties at 733 245h St. N.W. and the rear of 2312 H St. N.W. for a combined price off $15,000. The committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/09/1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Text on folder "Authorization for purchase of 2104-6-8-10 Pennsylvania Avenue at total cost of $190,000. (Sq. 75-Lots 28, 27, 839, 838) Ratification of authorizations of Chmn Lawson and Acting Pres. Colclough to purchase the following properties: 2104 Eye St. (Sq. 77 - Lot 28); 600 and 612 22nd St. (Sq. 57 - Lots 49 &43) 913 22nd St. (Sq. 75 - Lot 817) Rear of 919 22nd St. (Sq. 75 - Lot 843). Treasurer authorized to pay no more than $12,000 for purchase of 729 22nd St. (Sq. 79 - Lot 33). Approval of recommendation that authority granted B & L Committee at Board Mtg. Oct 8, 1959, be amended to include the following provision: that the President of the Univ., with the concurrence of the Chmn. of the Comm., be authorized to make purchases of property for $25,000 or less, within the limitations. Treasurer was requested to secure an appraisal of 813-17-21 23rd St. (Sq. 55, Lots 812, 815, 843). Treasurer reported about a piece of property in Law Center Square. The owner recently died; the administrator of his estate said that the Univ. will be given first consideration if property becomes available for sale."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/15/1959 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Text on Folder "Approval of recommendation that during 1956-60 fiscal year the Committee on B & L authorized to purchase properties within expenditure of $400,000 for the fiscal year in certain squares. Approval of recommendation that during 1956-60 fiscal the Finance Committee be authorized to mortgage University income-producing properties to the extent of $400,000 to carry out the property acquisition to program recommended by the Buildings and Lands Committee. See Finance Committee folder for signed minutes."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/08/1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Text on Folder "Under authority granted by Board the following properties were purchased: Square 40, Lot 825; Square 77, Lot 829; Square 77, Lot 828. The Committee authorized Treasurer to purchase Square 57, Lot 27 at a price not to exceed $14,500 from the Pairo Fund; The Committee authorized Treasurer to purchase Square 55, Lot B at $13,000 from general surplus funds; The Committee approved the purchase of Square 119, Lot 805 at $45,000; The Committee approved the purchase of Square 77, Lot 33 at $17,500; The Committee authorized the Treasurer to purchase Square 75, Lot 33 at $12,000; The Committee authorized the Treasurer to purchase Square 57, Lot 834 at $12,500 from Pairo Fund; Purchases in Square 57 can be cared for from Pairo Fund, purchases in Squares 40 and 75 from Surplus Hospital Funds, and remaining purchases from surplus in General University Funds."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/03/1958 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Text on Folder "Recommendation that resolution authorizing the execution of a loan agreement with the United States of America for the financing of the purchase and remodeling of Dolly Madison and John Quincy Adams Halls be presented to the Board; Recommendation that resolution be issued to the Riggs National Bank for the purpose of borrowing be presented to the Board. This resolution modifies the present resolution re the repayment of the loan and it increases the amount to be borrowed; Recommendation that a resolution defining the policy of the Board with respect to the manner in which funds received by the University under grants for or in aid of research should be treated be presented to the Board; Approval of the re-employment of Price Waterhose & Co. as University Auditors for the fiscal year ending August 31, 1959."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/16/1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Text on folder "Approval of recommendation to offer from $12,000 to $12,500 for Lot 27, Square 57 to the heirs of the deceased owner; Discussion of purchase of Keystone Apartments, purchase of a lot on 19th Street frontage of Square 119, air conditioning of office rooms, and the Urban Renewal Project Area Project for the University area. It was decided these should be considered at a special Board Meeting."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/01/1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Text on folder "No minutes were taken at this meeting. Enclosed is a report presented to the Board about the meeting."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/10/1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Text on folder "The meeting was recessed to meet again on Thursday, May 1, 1958."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/20/1957 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Text on Folder "Discussion of property the University might be interested in purchasing: Keystone Apartments - Committee authorized securing of appraisal; Square 77, Lots 812-816, - Owner asking $20 per sq. ft. Committee suggested Treasurer continue negotiating; Square 57, Lot 826 - owner set minimum price of $10,000. Committee authorized offer of $10,000 and possibility of $11,000; Square 57, right of way - appraised at $1,000, delinquent taxes of about 750. Committee felt way to obtain property was through tax title. Treasurer is to check with University Counsel concerning procedure; Square 75, Lot 805 - owner would accept $10,500. Committee authorized offer of $8,500; Square 75, Lot 829 - appraised at $38,000 and offered for $32,000. Committee felt the property was desirable but University does not have funds to buy at this time. The President suggested the Committee should lay down a policy of priority in considering properties offered."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/13/1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Text on folder "Application made to the Housing and Home Finance Agency for a loan of $1,250,000 to acquire and remodel two dormitories at interest rate of 2 7/8%, the loan to be amortized over a 40-year period has received preliminary approval and the funds reserved; Flagler Apartment was purchased for $425,000 as recommended by the Board; Recommendation for purchase of the Woodside Apartment at corner of 19th and H Streets at a price not to exceed $450.000; Report of Treasurer of proposal to remodel the Flagler Apartment for women students and the Woodside for men. A rough estimate of the cost of remodeling these apartments is $300,000 each. It was agreed these estimates were high; President Marvin suggested the application for funds be increased to make available $1,500,000. The Committee asked that a statement be prepared for presentation to the Board."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/02/1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Text on folder "Recommendation for purchase of the Flagler Apartments at 736 22nd Street, N.W. (Lot 840 in Square 56). Cost of purchase to be applicable to final loan application for federal funds from the Housing and Home Finance Agency for dormitory facilities; Report on progress re properties in Squares 77 and 119."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/13/1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Text on folder "Treasurer Herzog polled by telephone the members of the Committee. Approval was granted for purchase of Lot 829 in Square 41, known as 804 23rd Street, N.W., at price of $31,000."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/26/1957 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Text on folder "Approval of sale of residence of late Homer Stille Cummings at 4308 Forest Lane, N.W., at a price of $75,000.00 net. Executors to be so advised."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/17/1957 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Text on folder "President had told Medical Staff Exec. Committee that liquor ought not be brought into the Hospital; President recommended that Univ. should acquire or build housing for administrative units housed in old houses at the present time; As one of the legatees in the will of Homer S. Cummings, authorization was given to accept offer of $69,5000 by Vice President of U.S. for the Cummings' home; Square 119, 19th and H. Treasurer authorized to see if Lots 15, 16 and 21 could be purchased at appraised valuations; Purchase of Lots 35 to 39 inclusive in Square 57 at a price not to exceed $36,250, and Lot 42 in Square 57 at not to exceed $14,000.00; Treasurer to get appraisals for Lots 34, 816 and 817 if not in excess of appraisal; Authorization to offer $28,500 for Lot 829 in Square 41; Authorization to offer $16,500 for Lot 22 in Square 40, and to offer an amount not exceeding the appraised valuation, or $23,000, for Lot 25 in Square 40; Decision to ask Board for policy in regard to investing University funds in the area if it would carry itself and bring 5% return; Authorization to offer $21,000 for Lot 13 in Square 103; Offer of $100,000 for Lots 27, 28, 838, and 839 in Square 75, authorized at meeting 11/21/56, was withdrawn; Preliminary discussion about purchase of 7 acres in country to be used to house dogs used experimentally by Medical School, Hospital, and Cancer Clinic."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/27/1956 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Text on folder "Approval of purchase of Lots 11-17 in Square 57, 614-626 22nd Street, N.W.; Proposal to relocate the freeway so that it would not pass through Squares 40, 41 and 42 owned by Univ. Committees voted to have a brief prepared with help of legal counsel, appoint a committee to make appropriate contact on this matter. "
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/13/1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Text on folder "Discussion of the University's protest against present proposed location of the freeway which results in property loss in Squares 40, 41 and 42 and interferes with Medical Center; Loan under College Housing program for two dormitories. Authorized Treasurer to make preliminary application for $1,250,000 for acquisition and remodeling of existing apartment buildings for dormitories; University policy regarding purchase of pending settlement of the redevelopment plan was discussed. No decision was reached."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/21/1956 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Text on folder "Presentation of preliminary plan for University by University planners, to be presented to National Capital Planning Commission in protesting location of the freeway; Approval for purchase of lots from Judge Munter at total price of $165,000: Square 42, Lots 807 and 809; Square 57, Lots 19, 20, 800, 801, 832; Square 57, Lots 808 and 809; Square 75, Lots 21, 837, 836, 833. Approval for purchase of lots from Oliver T. Carr at $100,000; Square 75, Lots 28, 27, 839, 838. Decision against purchase of Lot 22 in Square 75 from Mr. Carr because of asking price; Approval to renew offer for apt. house on Lot 829 in Square 41, known as 804 23rd Street, N.W. at $27,500."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/23/1956 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Text on folder "A quorum was not present. Re: Purchase of Lot 827 in Square 122, S.E. corner of 19th and F Streets, N.W. owned by Church Orphanage Assn. of St. John's Church; Trustee Tompkins had recommended that University offer $400,000 for this property. Since no quorum was present, the Committee counseled President to see what action could be taken regarding purchase; Re: 2 properties in Square 119. No action or recommendation. For signed minutes - see folder of Executive Committee."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/17/1956 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Text on folder "Approval of purchase of Northwest Corner 20th and H Streets, N.W. (Lots 55, 56, 800, 801, 802, 803, 804 and 805 in Square 101) at $180,000.00; Approval of purchase of 2107-2109 H St., N.W. (Lots 800 and 801 in Square 77) at $34,000; Consideration of purchase of property at 23rd and H Streets, N.W. adjoining Tompkins Hall of Engineering. Treasurer to secure information on the lease before action is taken; Preparation of preliminary plans for new building to be located next to the Tompkins Hall of Engineering was approved with certain suggestions to be carried out; Approval of employment of Mr. Henry S. Churchill and firm of Wheelwright, Stevenson, Langran, & Fanning as professional assistance for the University development plan. Subject to final approval of the Executive Committee; Approval to proceed in organizing an Advisory Committee on University Planning; Representative of Ford Foundation had asked for study of the University's needs. President submitted report that would require abut fifteen million dollars; Decision to submit a protest to the Board of Commissioners concerning present plans for location of the freeway through Squares 40, 41, and 42. Treasurer to prepare a letter which can be distributed to Committee members in advance of meeting planned for early in August to act upon this."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/03/1956 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Text on folder "Ratified action of Chairman Lawson and President Marvin in purchasing 804 222nd Street, N.W. (Lot 801 in Square 55) for $16,500.00; Voted to purchase Marion Apt. House, 2000 H Street, N.W. (Lot 39 in Square 102) at price not to exceed $140,000. To negotiate with seller; Proposed Wing to Tompkins Hall of Engineering. President authorized to go over sketches with Trustee Tompkins and to take up with Riggs National Bank the possibility of the extension of University's line of credit for balance of funds necessary; Attention was called to new zoning regulations in the District. To be discussed later; Presentation of statement by Attorney Hugh Obear relative to property owned by President Marvin in Square 40. Committee was appointed to work out proper basis for acquiring the property. (For signed copy of the minutes, see folder under EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE)."
  - Committee on Building Lands--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/06/1956 (Box 1, Folder 36)